This video demonstrates how to perform a front of the eye examination using the
anterior segment loop of the Arclight device.
Start with hand hygiene and introduce yourself.
Confirm the identity of the patient, explain the examination, and gain consent to perform it.
Initially take a few seconds to observe both eyes at the same time.
Look at the periorbitor, eyelids and eyes.
Commenting on any swelling, redness and discharge, as well as prominence of the eyes or abnormal
eyelid position.
Then perform a magnified examination using the arc light.
Switch on the white light and
hold the device close to your eye.
Slowly approach the patient's right eye first until
it is in focus.
This will be at around 6cm.
As the patient to move their eye outwards and
inwards, then up and down, while gently holding their eyelids.
Systematically noting a different
structures seen, thinking of them in groups.
The first group includes the upper and lower
eyelashes and lid margins.
The second includes a conjunctiva and sclera and the lower forenicks.
The third group is the cornea, the junction of this with a sclera called
the limbis and
the pupil, surrounded by the iris.
Once you've finished noting all these structures, now
Now select the blue light on the arc light.
With fluorescing dye, the tear film, areas of epithelial loss and disease will be highlighted.
The dye fluoresces brightly with the blue light.
Record on a diagram the sight and size of areas of epithelial loss and disease.
Finish by examining the superior tarsal plate.
Place a cotton bud on the upper lid, then gently lift the lashes upwards while slowly
pressing downwards with the bud.
observed with a naked eye, then bring in the arc light for a magnified view.
Repeat this
examination on the other eye.
Afterwards, thank the patient, summarise and record your findings
and repeat hand hygiene.
Please have a look at our other University of St Andrews Arc Light
Project videos.